Finding Aid for James J. Duderstadt Papers 1963-1997
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
James J. Duderstadt Papers 1963-1997 1970-1996
Duderstadt, James J., 1942-
9811 Aa 2
Nuclear engineer, professor and eleventh president of the University of Michigan (1988-1996), leader in efforts to transform the University of Michigan, and higher education generally, into a culturally diverse, financially secure, and technologically advanced institution. Collection consists of both paper and digital documents, including speeches, presentations, writings and images. Portions of the collection are restricted. This collection represents the "personal papers" of president Duderstadt. Other material relating to his presidency is located in the record group "University of Michigan. President."
23.5 linear feet
2144 digital files 160.5 Mb
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The Duderstadt Papers (donor no. 8513 ) were transferred to the library in several accessions. The first paper material arrived in 1996 and the first digital material in 1997.
Access and Restrictions
The James J. Duderstadt collection is comprised of paper and digital subgroups. The entire paper subgroup is open for research. Series within the digital subgroup that are open for research are the Speeches, Presentations and Legacy files.
Series within the digital subgroup that are restricted until July 1, 2030 are:
Ideas
Position Papers
Strategy
Write Files
Nuclear engineer and eleventh President of the University of Michigan, James J. Duderstadt worked both to position the university as a leader in higher education and to transform the university into a new institutional "model" for higher education --an institutional model that could readily adapt to the changing needs of society.
Born on December 5, 1942 in Iowa, Duderstadt was raised in Carollton, Missouri, a small farming community of 4,000 persons. Duderstadt earned his B.S. in electrical engineering (summa cum laude), Yale University (1964); M.S. in engineering science, California Institute of Science (1965); and Ph.D. in engineering science and physics, California Institute of Technology (1967). Duderstadt's dissertation won the American Nuclear Society Mark Mills award, an honor presented to the nation's most outstanding Ph.D. dissertation in nuclear science and engineering. He married a high school classmate, Anne Marie Lock, in 1964. The Duderstadts have two daughters: Susan and Katharine.
After completing his master's and doctoral degrees in just three years, Duderstadt held a postdoctoral fellowship at the U.S. Atomic Energy Commission located in Los Alamos, New Mexico. The project involved the development of a nuclear rocket intended to fly to Mars. However, the NASA project lost funding, and in 1969 Duderstadt accepted an appointment as assistant professor of nuclear engineering at the University of Michigan, Ann Arbor. Duderstadt was promoted to the rank of associate professor in 1972 and achieved the status of full professor in 1976.
In the classroom, Duderstadt was the recipient of many awards for both his teaching and research efforts including Outstanding Nuclear Engineering Educator Award in 1974 and College of Engineering Outstanding Teacher in 1980. He was the primary supervisor for twenty-two doctoral dissertations, co-authored several engineering textbooks, and published over sixty journal articles in the areas of nuclear reactor theory, radiation transport, kinetic theory and statistical mechanics, plasma physics, and computer simulation.
In 1981, Professor Duderstadt was appointed dean of the University of Michigan's College of Engineering. At age 38, he was the youngest person ever to be appointed dean in the history of the college. His appointment occurred at the same time the state of Michigan was suffering from a downturn in the economy due to the effects of a national recession in the automobile industry. However, despite the economic atmosphere of the early 1980s, Duderstadt established the college as a "high priority" both in the university and in the state. He secured additional financial support from state, corporate, and private sources. During this period, the College of Engineering general fund went from $11 million to $34 million; private fund-raising grew from $2 million per year to $7 million per year; and federal and industrial sponsored research support rose from $16 million per year to $36 million per year during the last year of his tenure.
As dean of the College of Engineering, Duderstadt was also instrumental in the development of several high technology research initiatives. Major programmatic initiatives included: The Center for Research on Integrated Manufacturing; The Center for Machine Intelligence; The Center for Advanced Electronics and Optics Technology; and the Computer Aided Engineering Network (CAEN). Academic programs introduced under his direction were the Electrical Engineering and Computer Science (EECS) and Applied Physics programs.
By 1986, Duderstadt had "rebuilt" the Engineering campus and reestablished the prestige of the college within the university and state of Michigan. In that spring, Duderstadt stated, "The job in Engineering is winding down. We've accomplished what we set out to do." That spring he was appointed University of Michigan's Provost and Vice President for Academic Affairs.
As provost, Duderstadt's role was that of chief academic and chief budget officer. He also held approval responsibility for all faculty and academic staff appointments. The composition of the Ann Arbor campus at that time included 35,000 students, 3400 faculty, 15,000 staff members, a total operating budget of $1.2 billion per year, and a General Fund budget of $430 million per year.
Duderstadt's appointment to Provost and Vice President for Academic Affairs marked another "first" at the University. He was the first engineer to be appointed to this position. Duderstadt's appointment began during the final year of the university's "Five Year Plan" a plan focused on budget reallocation and reduction implemented by the university in reaction to a dramatic decrease in state support that began in the early 1980s. As provost, Duderstadt worked to shift the university's stance from "reactive to pro-active" by instilling an approach towards the external environment that was challenging rather than threatening. To achieve this objective, he implemented a series of well planned strategic retreats with key university administrators and academic units.
Duderstadt was just in the second year of his appointment as provost when President Harold Shapiro announced on April 28, 1987 that he had accepted the presidency at Princeton University. Former President Robben W. Fleming served as Interim President and on June 10, 1988, the Regents of the University named James J. Duderstadt the 11th president of the University of Michigan.
As president of the university, Duderstadt maintained a full steam ahead, energetic management style. He can be credited for instituting several changes in the cultural and physical landscape of Michigan. Most significantly, Duderstadt worked to alter the ethnic and racial composition of students, faculty, and staff at the university. His vision was to "build a community that values and respects and, indeed, draws its intellectual strength from the rich diversity of peoples of different races, cultures, religions, nationalities, and beliefs." His vision of a multicultural community for the twenty-first century resulted in a strategic plan for the university titled The Michigan Mandate: A Strategic Linking of Academic Excellence and Social Diversity. In addition to the "Michigan Mandate," Duderstadt worked to create a more equitable environment for women at the university as evidenced in "The Michigan Agenda." In this paper, Duderstadt challenged the university -- "By the Year 2000, the University of Michigan will become the leader among American universities in promoting and achieving the success of women of diverse backgrounds as faculty, students, and staff." Taken together, the Michigan Mandate and the Michigan Agenda outlined his vision for the future of minorities and women at the university.
The contours of the campus landscape also shifted significantly during the Duderstadt tenure. New construction, renovation, and major improvements were realized through an enthusiastic fund-raising campaign called the "Campaign for Michigan." The Campaign effort raised over $1 billion dollars and paved the way for the implementation of a major plan to strengthen the university's infrastructure. In sum, the Campaign effort led to the rebuilding of the Central and Medical campuses, expansion of the North Campus, renovation of the Athletic Campus, and the development of a landscaping plan for the entire campus. New construction included the Lurie Engineering Center, the Media Union, Cancer and Geriatrics Center, Institute of Continuing Legal Education, and the Francois-Xavier Bagnoud Building for Aerospace Research.
In addition to his efforts in shaping the campus both culturally and physically, Duderstadt can also be credited with overseeing the development of several research initiatives. A selection of new initiatives includes the Media Union, the Institute for the Humanities, the Institute of Molecular Medicine, and the Davidson Institute for Emerging Economies.
On September 27, 1995, President Duderstadt shocked the university community with the announcement that he would be leaving the position effective June 30, 1996. In an open letter to the community announcing his decision Duderstadt stated, "Working together, we have indeed built a truly extraordinary university. But we have built a university for the twentieth century, and that century is rapidly coming to an end. It is now time to lead the University in new directions, to transform ourselves to better serve a rapidly changing world. And I believe that such new directions may benefit best from new leadership, fresh visions, and untapped energy."
Upon his departure as president of the University of Michigan, Duderstadt returned to the classroom as Professor of Science and Technology at Michigan. In addition, he heads the Millennium Project. The Millennium Project is a research center in the Media Union concerned with the impact of technology on research and teaching. Information about current research and a selection of Duderstadt's "legacy documents" are available on-line at: [http://milproj.ummu.umich.edu].
Summary of positions held at the University of Michigan
1969-1972 Assistant Professor
1972-1976 Associate Professor
1976- Professor
1981-1986 Dean, College of Engineering
1986-1988 Provost and Executive Vice-President for Academic Affairs
1988-1996 President
1996- President Emeritus and University Professor of Science and Engineering
The Duderstadt collection is organized into two subgroups: Paper Documents and Digital Documents, each of which include several series and subseries.
Paper Documents
Biographical / Background
Speeches and Accompanying Material
Miscellaneous by Subject
Miscellaneous by Date
1981 -1982
1983-1984
1985-1986
1986
1987
1988
1989
1990
1991
1991-1992
1993
1994
1995
1996
Computer Printouts of Speeches
Position Papers
Publications (Legacy Documents)
Presentations
Correspondence
Research
Topical Files
Teaching
Presidential Transition
Strategic Planning
Digital Documents
Speeches
1986-1987 Speeches
1987-1988 Speeches
1988-1989 Speeches
1989-1990 Speeches
1990-1991 Speeches
1991-1992 Speeches
1992-1993 Speeches
1994-1995 Speeches
1995-1996 Speeches
Athletic Talks-Speeches
Idea Files
1986-1987 Ideas
1987-1988 Ideas
1988-1989 Ideas
1989-1990 Ideas
1990-1991 Ideas
1991-1992 Ideas
1992-1993 Ideas
1993-1994 Ideas
1994-1995 Ideas
Strategy
1986-1987 Strategy
1987-1988 Strategy
1989-1990 Strategy
1990-1991 Strategy
1994-1995 Strategy
1995-1996 Strategy
1996-1997 Strategy
Position Papers
1986-1987 Position Papers
1987-1988 Position Papers
1988-1989 Position Papers
1989-1990 Position Papers
1990-1991 Position Papers
1991-1992 Position Papers
1992-1993 Position Papers
1993-1994 Position Papers
1994-1995 Position Papers
1995-1996 Position Papers
1996-1997 Position Papers
Presentations
1987-1988 Presentations
1988-1989 Presentations
1989-1990 Presentations
1990-1991 Presentations
1991-1992 Presentations
1992-1993 Presentations
1993-1994 Presentations
1994-1995 Presentations
1995-1996 Presentations
1996-1997 Presentations
Write Files
1988 and earlier Write
1988-1989 Write
1989-1990 Write
1990-1991 Write
1991-1992 Write
1992-1993 Write
1993-1994 Write
1994-1995 Write
1995-1996 Write
1996-1997 Write
Legacy Documents
Digital Images
The James J. Duderstadt papers (19 linear feet and 160.5 megabytes in 2,144 computer files) span the years from 1963 to 1997, although the bulk of the material covers 1970 to 1996. The collection, consisting mainly of Speeches, Position Papers, and Presentations, effectively documents Duderstadt's vision, agenda, and planning process. There are two subgroups in the collection: Paper Documents and Digital Documents.
The Paper Documents subgroup is comprised of ten series: Biographical / Background Material, Speeches and Accompanying Material, Computer Printouts of Speeches, Position Papers, Publications, Presentations, Correspondence, Research, Topical Files (Pre-Presidency), and Teaching. It includes a few papers from his years as engineering dean and his term as provost, along with a substantial amount of material from his years as professor of nuclear engineering and as president of the university.
A second subgroup, Digital Documents, is comprised of material created and maintained in electronic form (utilizing a number of software programs), and is particularly strong for representing Duderstadt's entire term as president of the university. The subgroup includes eight series: Speeches, Idea Files, Strategy, Position Papers, Presentations, Write Files and Legacy Files. The digital files of speeches and position papers frequently contain various and well-organized iterations of key documents. Of particular note are the Strategy Files, which hold substantial planning documents, many designed to encourage and promote vigorous response to change at many levels within the university. The subgroup also contains a series of Digital Images, most of which appeared in the 1996 publication Rebuilding the University: 1986-1996.
Subjects:
Duderstadt, James J., 1942-; Education, Higher--Michigan.; Education, Higher--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Media Union (University of Michigan); Minorities--Education, Higher--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Minorities--Michigan--Ann Arbor--Education.; Minorities--Michigan--Ann Arbor--Employment.; Universities and colleges--Michigan.; University of Michigan. Board of Regents.; University of Michigan. President.; University of Michigan--Administration.; University of Michigan--Buildings.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan--Finance.; University of Michigan--History.; University of Michigan--Planning.; University of Michigan--Provost and Vice-President.; University of Michigan--Research.; University of Michigan--Sports.; University of Michigan--Students.; Women--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Women college students--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Women college teachers--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Women in education--Michigan.
Subjects:Visual Materials
University of Michigan--Buildings.
Genre/Form:
Computer files.; Digital images.; Photographs.
- Paper Documents
  The material in the James J. Duderstadt Paper Documents subgroup was transferred to the Bentley Historical Library shortly after Duderstadt's presidency at the University of Michigan ended in 1996. It includes a few papers from his years as engineering dean and his term as provost, along with a substantial amount of material from his years as professor of nuclear engineering and as president of the university. Researchers should note that there is also paper documentation specific to the Duderstadt presidency (as well as audio and visual material) held at the Bentley in the following record groups: University of Michigan, President; University of Michigan, Provost and Executive Vice President for Academic Affairs; and the College of Engineering. The Paper Documents subgroup is organized into ten series:
  - Biographical / Background Material 1970-1996, 0.5 linear feet
    The Biographical / Background Material (.50 linear ft., 1970-1996), including resume, newspaper clippings, personnel papers, and some correspondence, although sparse, provides context and background to the other series in the subgroup. This series contains detailed biographical data and lists of published work for 1968 to 1996. Additional papers for the years 1981 to 1987 chronicle Duderstadt's rise from 1981 at age 38 as the youngest dean in the history of the College of Engineering to 1987, the year before he became eleventh president of the university.
    - Academic Personnel Record 1974-1979 (Box 1)
    - Calendar, partially utilized 1986 (Box 1)
    - Cartoons (Box 1)
    - Clippings 1974-1995, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - General (includes vitas) 1984-1996 (Box 1)
    - Personnel Papers 1982-1987 (Box 1)
    - Portraits (various dates) (Box 1)
    - Student Record Transcripts (Box 1)
  - Speeches and Accompanying Material 1981-1996, 6.5 linear feet
    The Speeches and Accompanying Material series (4.50 linear ft., 1981-1992) is by far the bulk of the subgroup, containing files created during Duderstadt's provost years through the earlier half of his tenure as president. There are speeches in the series for the years 1986 through 1992, with the greatest concentration 1988 to 1990. During these later years Duderstadt often gave numerous speeches a day across the state and on the Michigan campus. Topics range widely from key policy statements, such as various iterations of the Michigan Mandate, to legislative addresses and routine welcomes and alumni addresses.
    The speeches are, for the most part, arranged chronologically with approximately one foot arranged by subject. The files in this series are particularly valuable because they are enriched with "accompanying material" --guest lists, programs, correspondence, notes, overheads, various versions of the same speech, annotated copies of speeches and drafts, and similar documents. It is sometimes possible to trace the evolution of an idea or to gather understanding of the audience for which a speech was prepared. Particularly for completeness (and also for more efficient subject access across the files through keyword searching) researchers interested in Duderstadt speeches should also review the large number of speech files in the Digital Documents subgroup.
    - Arranged by Subject
      - Alumni Relations 1988-1990 (Box 1)
      - Background Materials and List of Talks 1986-1989 (Box 1)
      - Coaches Talks 1988-1990 (Box 1)
      - Engineering Education 1985 (Box 1)
      - Faculty Awards 1986 (Box 1)
      - Freshman Convocations 1988-1994 (Box 1)
      - Graduate Student Welcomes 1989-1990 (Box 1)
      - Legislative Addresses 1988-1989 (Box 1)
      - Major Gifts, undated (Box 1)
      - Michigan Mandate Status Reports 1990-1991 (Box 1)
      - Miscellaneous 1988 (Box 1)
      - Parent Orientations 1988-1990 (Box 1)
      - President's Weekend Speeches 1988-1990 (Box 1)
      - State Relations Talks 1986, undated (Box 1)
      - Welcome Addresses 1988-1989 (Box 1)
    - Arranged by Date
      - 1981-1982, 2 folders (Box 1)
      - 1983-1984, 3 folders (Box 1)
      - 1985-1986, 1 folders (Box 2)
    - 1986
      - Ann Arbor Rotary May 18, 1986 (Box 2)
      - University of Michigan, Dearborn May 26, 1986 (Box 2)
      - Iacocca-Fraser Commission May 29, 1986 (Box 2)
      - Medical Dinner May 31, 1986 (Box 2)
      - Problem Challenge / Michigan's Future May 31, 1986 (Box 2)
      - AAES, June 23 (Box 2)
      - Housing Presentation August 20, 1986 (Box 2)
      - Parent's Orientation Talk August 31, 1986 (Box 2)
      - Faculty Meeting September 6, 1986 (Box 2)
      - Alumni, September 7 (Box 2)
      - Literature, Science and Arts, Faculty September 8, 1986 (Box 2)
      - Center for Research on Teaching and Learning New Faculty September 9, 1986 (Box 2)
      - Experimental Research in Electronic Submission Program Talk September 10, 1986 (Box 2)
      - E.O. Lawrence Award September 11, 1986 (Box 2)
      - Alumni Merit Scholars September 15, 1986 (Box 2)
      - Alumni Talks September 18, 1986 (Box 2)
      - Engineering NAC Meeting September 26, 1986 (Box 2)
      - Comments October 4, 1986 (Box 2)
      - Dentistry October 13, 1986 (Box 2)
      - Yale Alumni Association of Michigan October 30, 1986 (Box 2)
      - National Honor Society November 10, 1986 (Box 2)
      - Dentistry November 20, 1986 (Box 2)
      - IBM Luncheon November 20, 1986 (Box 2)
      - Generic Leadership Address December 4, 1986 (Box 2)
      - Plan to Respond to the Challenge of Leadership, December 4 (Box 2)
      - Generic Leadership Address December 11, 1986 (Box 22)
      - Masons May 27, 1986 (Box 22)
      - Iacocca-Fraser Commission May 29, 1986 (Box 22)
      - Majoring Hanging Decisions June 1986 (Box 22)
      - HTS Discussions June 3, 1986 (Box 22)
      - Budget Priorities Committee June 26, 1986 (Box 22)
      - All Campus Development Staff June 27, 1986 (Box 22)
      - Medical School September 2, 1986 (Box 22)
      - Art Faculty Meeting September 2, 1986 (Box 22)
      - Masons September 7, 1986 (Box 22)
      - Questions September 7, 1986 (Box 22)
      - Educating for a World of Technological Change September 7, 1986 (Box 22)
      - The Future of Engineering Education September 7, 1986 (Box 22)
      - LSA Faculty Meeting September 17, 1986 (Box 22)
      - Alumni Talk September 22, 1986 (Box 22)
      - UM Dearborn October 22, 1986 (Box 22)
    - 1987
      - Sets of Talks 1987 (Box 2)
      - Physics January 21, 1987 (Box 2)
      - Research Excellence Fund Symposium February 12, 1987 (Box 2)
      - Space Physics Research Lab February 13, 1987 (Box 2)
      - Alumni Talk February 15, 1987 (Box 2)
      - High Tech in Michigan March 1, 1987 (Box 2)
      - NIH Predoctoral Genetics Training Grant (Box 2)
      - Terman Talk March 10, 1987 (Box 2)
      - United States / Japan Conference April 14, 1987 (Box 2)
      - Let's Do It Right April 15, 1987 (Box 2)
      - Yale Talk April 16, 1987 (Box 2)
      - Alumni Talk May 7, 1987 (Box 2)
      - Educating For a World of Change May 8, 1987 (Box 2)
      - Role of Research University in Undergraduate Education, May (Box 2)
      - Michigan High Tech May 1987 (Box 2)
      - Challenge of Equal Opportunity June 5, 1987 (Box 2)
      - National Nursing Symposium June 11, 1987 (Box 2)
      - National Center for Manufacturing Sciences July 20, 1987 (Box 2)
      - Integrated Technology Instruction Center August 1987 (Box 2)
      - Michigan's Challenge: The Age of Knowledge Fall 1987 (Box 2)
      - Challenge of Diversity and Excellence September 2, 1987 (Box 2)
      - Freshman Convocation September 10, 1987 (Box 2)
      - Challenge of Leadership: A Mission of the 21st Century September 20, 1987 (Box 2)
      - Senate Assembly September 21, 1987 (Box 2)
      - Grand Rapids Economics Club October 1987 (Box 2)
      - Educating for a World of Change / Grad School Conference November 14, 1987 (Box 2)
      - Enrollment Study November 16, 1987 (Box 2)
      - Challenge of Diversity and Excellence December 7, 1987 (Box 2)
      - Parent's Orientation December 31, 1987 (Box 2)
      - Ethics and Values Conference March 7, 1987 (Box 22)
      - "Terman" Talk 0.9 March 10, 1987 (Box 22)
      - Education for the Age of Knowledge March 23, 1987 (Box 22)
      - Master Notes: The Age of Knowledge April 2, 1987 (Box 22)
      - US-Japan Conference April 14, 1987 (Box 22)
      - Some Thoughts April 28, 1987 (Box 22)